<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The remors of conscyence Here begynneth certayne demonstracyons by our lorde to all synfull persones with the remors of mannes conscynce to the regarde of the bounte of our lorde.</title>
            <author>Lichfield, William, d. 1448.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1500</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 15 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10608</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20881.3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100440</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836280</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836280</idno>
            <idno type="VID">540</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10608)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 540)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1360:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The remors of conscyence Here begynneth certayne demonstracyons by our lorde to all synfull persones with the remors of mannes conscynce to the regarde of the bounte of our lorde.</title>
                  <author>Lichfield, William, d. 1448.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12+] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Wynkyn de Worde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>ca. 1510]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By William Lichfield.</note>
                  <note>Some manuscript texts are titled "The complaynt of God".</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Woodcut illustration on title page.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 20883.</note>
                  <note>In this edition, title page line 4 begins: remors.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; lacks all after a6.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Conscience --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:540:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 78 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:540:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 78 -->
            <p>The remors of conſcyence.</p>
            <p>¶Here begynneth certayne demonſtracyons by our lorde to all ſynfull perſones with the remors of mannes conſcyence to the regarde of the bounte of our lorde.</p>
            <figure/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:540:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 79 -->
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="poetic_dialogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:540:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 79 -->
            <sp>
               <speaker>Deus.</speaker>
               <l>OVr gracyous god mooſt in magnyfycence</l>
               <l>His mercyfull eyen caſteth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heuen on hy</l>
               <l>Seynge his creatures in deedly vyolence</l>
               <l>Hymſelfe complayneth by pyte full ruthfully</l>
               <l>Saynge o man deuoyde of intellygence</l>
               <l>Open thyn eeres vnto my call and cry</l>
               <l>And tell me yf I haue done to the offence</l>
               <l>That thou forſakeſt me wyllyngly</l>
               <l>Man ſuche a loue to the I dyde take</l>
               <l>This worlde in ſeuen dayes whan I it wrought</l>
               <l>Thou was the laſt thynge that I dyde make</l>
               <l>Bycauſe I wolde thou wanted nought</l>
               <l>What thynge the myght helpe dyde not lake</l>
               <l>That at thy nede yf it were ſought</l>
               <l>Fowle / fyſſhe all thynge for thy ſake</l>
               <l>For thy comforte all was forth brought</l>
               <l>Moreouer I gaue the that dygnyte</l>
               <l>All beeſtes to bowe the vntyll</l>
               <l>I made the alſo lyke vnto me</l>
               <l>And gaue the connynge and free wyll</l>
               <l>Me to ſerue that thou ſholde ſe</l>
               <l>To choſe the good and leue the yll</l>
               <l>I aſke no thynge agayne of the</l>
               <l>But loue thy ſouerayne as it is ſkyll</l>
               <l>But vnto this takeſt thou none entente</l>
               <l>Thou tourneſt fro me full vnkyndly</l>
               <l>On loues vnlefull thy loue is lente</l>
               <l>Thy herte beholdeth not heuen ſo hye</l>
               <l>For all the goodes I haue the ſente</l>
               <l>The lyſteth not ones to ſaye gramercye</l>
               <l>In tyme to come or thou repente</l>
               <l>Man make amendes or that thou dye</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:540:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 80 -->
               <speaker>Homo.</speaker>
               <l>A cryſten ſoule conceyued in ſynne</l>
               <l>Receyued in conſcyence thus complaynynge</l>
               <l>He fell downe flatte with dolefull dynne</l>
               <l>And ſayd lorde mercy ſouerayne kynge</l>
               <l>I mooſt vnkynde wretche of man kynne</l>
               <l>I knowe I am thy traytour vntrue in my lyuynge</l>
               <l>This wycked lyfe that I lyue in</l>
               <l>I may it nought hyde from thy knowynge</l>
               <l>I want wordes and alſo wytte</l>
               <l>Of thy kyndneſſe to ſpeke a clauſe</l>
               <l>That I haue thou gaue me it</l>
               <l>Of thy goodnes withouten cauſe</l>
               <l>Though I haue greued the and do yet</l>
               <l>Thy benefaytes thou nought withdrawſe</l>
               <l>I haue deſerued to haue hell pytte</l>
               <l>So haue I lyued ayenſt thy lawſe</l>
               <l>But forde thou knoweſt mannes febleneſſe</l>
               <l>How frayle it is and hath ben aye</l>
               <l>For though the ſoule haue thy lykeueſſe</l>
               <l>Man is but fulſome erth and claye</l>
               <l>In ſynne conceyued and wretchedneſſe</l>
               <l>And to the ſoule rebell alwaye</l>
               <l>Fyrſt a man groweth as dooth greſſe</l>
               <l>And he waſteth after as floures or haye</l>
               <l>Syth man is than ſo frayle a thynge</l>
               <l>And thy power ſo grete in kynde</l>
               <l>This worlde is but a twynkelynge</l>
               <l>Thou mayſt deſtroye the myght of the fende</l>
               <l>With thy ryght lorde mercy mynge</l>
               <l>And to my ſore ſalue thou ſende</l>
               <l>Sore me repenteth of my myſtyuynge</l>
               <l>Mercy lorde I wyll amende</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:540:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 80 -->
               <speaker>Deus.</speaker>
               <l>Man I gaue the bodyly hele</l>
               <l>That thou ſholde it ſpende in my ſeruyce</l>
               <l>Fayrenes alſo and fetures fele</l>
               <l>Man what dooſt thou with all thyſe</l>
               <l>Thou with delytes of the deuyll dooſt dele</l>
               <l>Whiche is to me a grete deſpyſe</l>
               <l>Thou lyueſt a lecherous lyfe vnlele</l>
               <l>Fro yere to yere thou lyſt not ryſe</l>
               <l>Thou ſtudyeſt after nyce araye</l>
               <l>And makeſt grete coſt on thy clothynge</l>
               <l>To make the ſemely as who ſholde ſaye</l>
               <l>Thou coudeſt amende my makynge</l>
               <l>Thou purpoſeſt the daye by daye</l>
               <l>To ſet my people to ſynnynge</l>
               <l>Thy wretched wyll thou foloweſt alwaye</l>
               <l>What ende ſynne hath y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> thynkeſt no thynge</l>
               <l>In Noes tyme bycauſe of ſynne</l>
               <l>And for lecherye in eſpecyall</l>
               <l>What vengeau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce came than to ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes kynne</l>
               <l>Saue .viii. perſones drowned were all</l>
               <l>On ſodome and gomor and the men within</l>
               <l>How I made fyre and brymſtone fall</l>
               <l>Fro heuen on them that bode therin</l>
               <l>For ſynne were deſtroyed bothe grete &amp; ſmall</l>
               <l>Man weneſt thou my myght be leſſe</l>
               <l>Than it was than or that elles I</l>
               <l>Thou haſt now as moche wyckedneſſe</l>
               <l>As whan I ſmote the mooſt pyteouſty</l>
               <l>But yf thou wyll thy fautes redreſſe</l>
               <l>Though I now ſpare for my mercy</l>
               <l>Man thynke on my ryghtwyſneſſe</l>
               <l>And make amendes or that thou dye a .iii.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:540:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 81 -->
               <speaker>Homo.</speaker>
               <l>I wote well lorde ryghtfull thou arte</l>
               <l>And that ſynne muſt be punyſhed nede</l>
               <l>But one thynge holdeth in hope my herte</l>
               <l>Thy mercy paſeth my myſdede</l>
               <l>I knowe well that I may not ſterte</l>
               <l>I haue ſo done me ought to drede</l>
               <l>With beaute and with hodely quarte</l>
               <l>To ſerue the I haue taken no hede</l>
               <l>I haue myſpended my yonge age</l>
               <l>In ſynne and wantonneſſe alſo</l>
               <l>To ſerue god ſlowe / and loued to rage</l>
               <l>A gloton / a lechour I was bothe two</l>
               <l>I am worthy none other wage</l>
               <l>But for to dwell in endleſſe woo</l>
               <l>Alas why haue I ben outrage</l>
               <l>And ſerued the fende that is my foo</l>
               <l>But lorde in holy wryte rede we</l>
               <l>That thou forſakeſt no wretched wyght</l>
               <l>That leueth his ſynne and tourneth to the</l>
               <l>And to tourne to the haue I hyght</l>
               <l>Full proude and rebell haue I bene</l>
               <l>But now I take me to thy myght</l>
               <l>From hens for warde to be clene</l>
               <l>Ayenſt myn owne fleſſhe to fyght</l>
               <l>My fleſſhe to feble I wyll faſt</l>
               <l>My bones to trauayle and to tene</l>
               <l>And thrugh thy grace I am not agaſt</l>
               <l>What fore and ſekeneſſe on me be ſene</l>
               <l>To ſuffre whyle my lyfe may laſt</l>
               <l>For vtterly I wyll attende</l>
               <l>To punyſſhe that I haue treſpaſt</l>
               <l>Mercy I heſu I wyll amende</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:540:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 81 -->
               <speaker>Deus.</speaker>
               <l>Man I haue ſente the ſyluer and golde</l>
               <l>And all thy welth within thy wone</l>
               <l>To ſuſteyne the and thy houſholde</l>
               <l>And alſo other many one</l>
               <l>Thou myght haue holpen yonge and olde</l>
               <l>That ben dyſeaſed and woobe gone</l>
               <l>My ſeruauntes ſuffred bothe hungre and colde</l>
               <l>Relefe of the yet haue they none</l>
               <l>If thou gyue for my loue a farthynge</l>
               <l>Thou dooſt it with an heuy herte</l>
               <l>In almeſſe thou gyueſt no thynge</l>
               <l>For drede thou fall in pouerte</l>
               <l>In fleſſhely luſte and worldly lykynge</l>
               <l>What euer thou waſteſt mery thou arte</l>
               <l>Of ſuche I wyll haue a rekenynge</l>
               <l>At domes daye thou ſhalte not aſtarte</l>
               <l>Than ſhalte thou gyue a countes full ſtreyte</l>
               <l>How thou comeſt by thy good eche dele</l>
               <l>Whether with trouth or with deceyte</l>
               <l>And how thou ſpende it yll or wele</l>
               <l>None other grace thou after wayte</l>
               <l>As thou haſt wrought ſo ſhalte thou fele</l>
               <l>What ſhall than profyte thy good in plate</l>
               <l>Or poundes that thou of the people pele</l>
               <l>A clene conſcyence ſhall that daye</l>
               <l>More profyte the and more ſet by</l>
               <l>Than all the goodes or the monaye</l>
               <l>Than euer was vnder heuen or ſkye</l>
               <l>It wyll neuer helpe to plete nor praye</l>
               <l>For as ryght wyſe than deme wyll I</l>
               <l>And therfore man whyles thou may</l>
               <l>Make amendes or that thou dye</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:540:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 82 -->
               <speaker>Homo.</speaker>
               <l>I wote well lorde fro yere to yere</l>
               <l>Full gretely greued I the haue</l>
               <l>That I wolde nor thy mercy were</l>
               <l>My moders wombe had be my graue</l>
               <l>For what profyteth my lyuynge here</l>
               <l>But afterwarde I ſholde be ſaue</l>
               <l>But Iheſu as thou bought me dere</l>
               <l>Leue not my ſoule in hell caue</l>
               <l>My waſte expenſe I wyll withdrawe</l>
               <l>For waſte well called may it be</l>
               <l>For it was ſpended my booſt to lawe</l>
               <l>My name to bere on londe and ſe</l>
               <l>Well I wote me there not trowe</l>
               <l>Thought many a man of my countre</l>
               <l>If they me mette they dyde me not knowe</l>
               <l>Nor neuer yet herde ſpeke of me</l>
               <l>Falſly I haue wrought as wretche vnwyſe</l>
               <l>I myght haue goten me moche mede</l>
               <l>Had I it ſpente in goddes ſeruyce</l>
               <l>But thorugh thy grace lorde I am in drede</l>
               <l>As men that lyeth and may not ryſe</l>
               <l>For haue I and myn all our nede</l>
               <l>With the remenaunt lorde at thy deuyſe</l>
               <l>The poore and naked with cloth and fere</l>
               <l>Seke men that lyen in goddes bandes</l>
               <l>That haue no ſyluer for to ſpende</l>
               <l>And pryſoners bounde bothe fete and handes</l>
               <l>Ofte to vyſyte and them attende</l>
               <l>Whan Iſe them that in nede ſtandes</l>
               <l>Suche as I haue I ſhall them ſende</l>
               <l>Lorde let theſe werkes leſſe my bande</l>
               <l>And mercy Iheſu I wyll amende</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:540:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 82 -->
               <speaker>Deus.</speaker>
               <l>Man yf thou amendes wylte make</l>
               <l>Gyue thyn almeſſe of thyn owne goodes</l>
               <l>And ſethou werkes no man to wrake</l>
               <l>To venge ony other mennes modes</l>
               <l>If thou vntruly from ony take</l>
               <l>And therwith fynde forty theyr fodes</l>
               <l>Suche ſacrefyce I forſake</l>
               <l>They be to me as ſoure as wormewode</l>
               <l>The poore people thou dooſt oppreſſe</l>
               <l>With ſleyghtes and wyles many one</l>
               <l>Thou makeſt chyrches and do ſynge meſſe</l>
               <l>Thou mendeſt wayes where men ouer goue</l>
               <l>And ſome men curſe and ſome men bleſſe</l>
               <l>Whiche ſhall I here of theſe two</l>
               <l>If thou wylte haue grace as I geſſe</l>
               <l>Let all falſnes be fledde the fro</l>
               <l>The mothes that thy clothes ete</l>
               <l>And thou letteſt poore men go bare</l>
               <l>Thy drynke ſoureth and mouleth thy mete</l>
               <l>Wherwith the poore man myght well fare</l>
               <l>The ruſt that thy ſyluer dooth frete</l>
               <l>Thy goodes that euyll goten are</l>
               <l>They crye on the vengeaunce grete</l>
               <l>The for to ſpyll but yet I ſpare</l>
               <l>Withholdeſt here ayenſt the ryght</l>
               <l>From thy ſeruauntes vpon the crye</l>
               <l>Man oftentymes thou haſt me hyght</l>
               <l>Thou wolde amende and leue foly</l>
               <l>Thou ſpekeſt full fayre bothe daye &amp; nyght</l>
               <l>Thou brekeſt my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynually</l>
               <l>Yet is me lothe with the to fyght</l>
               <l>But make amendes or that thou dye</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:540:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 83 -->
               <speaker>Homo.</speaker>
               <l>Swete lorde I may not agaynſt ſaye</l>
               <l>I haue not holden that I the hyght</l>
               <l>I greue the gretely euery daye</l>
               <l>I do not as I had the plyght</l>
               <l>I wolde do well but welawaye</l>
               <l>With enemyes I am euer beſet</l>
               <l>Whan my ſoule fayne wolde the paye</l>
               <l>My fleſſhe is fyrſt that wyll me let</l>
               <l>And euer the fatter that I it fede</l>
               <l>Euer the freſſher it is my foo</l>
               <l>Yet bere it aboute I muſt nede</l>
               <l>Full feble it is it wyll me ſloo</l>
               <l>The worlde  /the fende / the fleſſhe they bede</l>
               <l>Some with well and ſome with woo</l>
               <l>What may I do with a wycked wede</l>
               <l>To fyght ayenſt thre enemyes ſoo</l>
               <l>Whan I enforce me otherwhyles</l>
               <l>And thynke I wyll lyue a true lyue</l>
               <l>And forſake all batayles and gyles</l>
               <l>The worlde byddeth me batayle belyue</l>
               <l>And but I wyll vſe wrethes and wyles</l>
               <l>The comyn voyce is I ſhall not tryue</l>
               <l>Some me ſcorneth and at me ſmyles</l>
               <l>And counte me but a kynde caytyue</l>
               <l>But now I thynke withſtondynge this</l>
               <l>To forſake falſnes withouten ende</l>
               <l>And reſtore that I toke amys</l>
               <l>And paye my dettes fayre and hende</l>
               <l>And to rewarde eche man his</l>
               <l>As reaſon is than wyll I ſpende</l>
               <l>And gyue myn almeſſe there nede is</l>
               <l>Mercy Iheſu I wyll amende</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:540:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 83 -->
               <speaker>Deus.</speaker>
               <l>Man I haue ſente the kyndly ſyght</l>
               <l>And vnderſtandynge ſkyll and wytte</l>
               <l>To rule thy ſelfe by reaſon ryght</l>
               <l>As reherfeth holy wrytte</l>
               <l>That clerely ſheweth the godly lyght</l>
               <l>How thou ſholde deedly ſynne forſake</l>
               <l>And on y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> maner thou pleaſe me myght</l>
               <l>What ayleth the thus fro me to ſhake</l>
               <l>Worldly rycheſſe ryall repayre</l>
               <l>In welth and thynges of Iolyte</l>
               <l>Fyſſhes beeſtes and byrdes of the ayre</l>
               <l>Theſe thynketh me ſemely for to ſe</l>
               <l>That thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> periſſheth &amp; dooth appayre</l>
               <l>Vnto thy ſyght thus pleaſynge be</l>
               <l>Well mayſt thou wytre I am full fayre</l>
               <l>Of whome eche thynge hath this beaute</l>
               <l>But man as thou wytleſſe were</l>
               <l>Thou lokeſt aye downwarde as a beeſt</l>
               <l>It behoueth the of me to here</l>
               <l>Foule ſpekynge is to the a feeſt</l>
               <l>I comforte the I make the chere</l>
               <l>And thou in wardly loueſt me leeſt</l>
               <l>I call the to me yere by yere</l>
               <l>Thou wylte not come at my requeſt</l>
               <l>As fro thy foo thou fro me feles</l>
               <l>I folowe the faſt and on the crye</l>
               <l>Thou wrappeſt the with all vanytees</l>
               <l>And thynke my ſpeche to the but folye</l>
               <l>And a thynge that nought is y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> wylte leſe</l>
               <l>My Ioye that laſteth endleſly</l>
               <l>Man yet vyce leue and vertue cheſe</l>
               <l>And make amendes or that thou dye</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:540:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 84 -->
               <speaker>Homo.</speaker>
               <l>Swete Iheſu none anſwere I can</l>
               <l>But ofte crye mercy with herte ſtable</l>
               <l>Alas for woo why is a man</l>
               <l>Worſe than a beeſt vnreaſonable</l>
               <l>All beeſtes ſythen the worlde began</l>
               <l>In kyndely werkynge ben durable</l>
               <l>Saue onely I of wyll wan</l>
               <l>That do full many dedes dampnable</l>
               <l>I was made to knowe my maker</l>
               <l>And to loue hym ouer all thynge</l>
               <l>And I a ſleper and neuer waker</l>
               <l>To take kynde knowynge of my kynge</l>
               <l>To tryfles haue I ben a grete hede taker</l>
               <l>A ſonge of ſorowe may I ſynge</l>
               <l>For had I ben of ſynne a forſaker</l>
               <l>Of cryſte ſholde I haue had ſome knowynge</l>
               <l>My ghooſtly eyen ben full of duſte</l>
               <l>Curſed couetyſe hath blynded me</l>
               <l>They ben blodeſhotten with fleſſhely luſte</l>
               <l>That heuenly kynge may I not ſe</l>
               <l>But lorde though I haue ben vniuſte</l>
               <l>Thorough helpe of thy benygnyte</l>
               <l>I hope to rubbe awaye the ruſte</l>
               <l>With repentaunce and grace of the</l>
               <l>And where that I haue afore this</l>
               <l>My wyll in worlde thynge haue ſpende</l>
               <l>From hens forwarde my purpoſe is</l>
               <l>Thy lawe to lerne to my lyues ende</l>
               <l>Thy .x. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes truly ywys</l>
               <l>Them to kepe I wyll me bende</l>
               <l>And there as I haue done amys</l>
               <l>Mercy Iheſu I wyll amende</l>
            </sp>
            <pb facs="tcp:540:7"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 84 -->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
